{"tossups": [{"question": "This experiment produced flashes of light called scintillations, which were seen on a zinc sulfide screen. One scientist analogized the results of this experiment to \"firing a 15-inch shell at a piece of tissue paper.\" This experiment was carried out by Hans Geiger and Ernest Marsden, which saw 1 of every 20,000 (*) alpha particles fired at a sheet of metal deflected more than 90 degrees, while some were deflected right back to the source. The results of this experiment had contradicted J.J. Thomson\u2019s plum pudding model of the atom. For 10 points, name this experiment that discovered the nucleus of the atom, conducted by Ernest Rutherford.", "answer": "Rutherford Gold Foil experiment [accept Rutherford experiment before \u201cRutherford\u201d; accept Geiger-Marsden experiment before mention]", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Rutherford Gold Foil experiment</u></b> [accept <b><u>Rutherford experiment</u></b> before \u201cRutherford\u201d; accept <b><u>Geiger-Marsden experiment</u></b> before mention]", "acceptable": ["Rutherford Gold Foil experiment", "Rutherford experiment", "Geiger-Marsden experiment"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "During an event in this country, Vasili Arkhipov prevented a war by deciding not to fire a torpedo from a B-59 submarine. During that event, a politician remarked \"We\u2019re eyeball to eyeball, and I think the other fellow just blinked.\" One leader of this nation led an attack on the Moncada Barracks. Franklin Pierce was shamed by a document advocating this country\u2019s annexation by the US, the (*) Ostend Manifesto. One leader of this nation delivered the \"History Will Absolve Me\" speech. This nation was the site of the Battle of San Juan Hill and the Bay of Pigs invasion. The USS Maine exploded in, for 10 points, what Caribbean island nation formerly led by Fidel Castro from Havana?", "answer": "Republic of Cuba", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Republic of Cuba</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Republic of Cuba"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In one poem, this author described a group of girls who \"went down to the beach (to play one day).\" In another poem, this author wrote about a character who shot \"onetwothreefourfive pigeons justlikethat\" and rode a \"watersmooth-silver stallion.\" In a third poem, this author wrote that \"noone (\"no one\") stooped to kiss [the title character\u2019s] face.\" That poem repeats the refrain (*) \"sun moon stars rain.\" This poet also wrote about a man who was \"more brave than me:more blond than you.\" This poet of \"Buffalo Bill's\" described a place \"with up so floating many bells down.\" For 10 points, name this poet of \"i sing of Olaf glad and big\" and \"anyone lived in a pretty how town,\" known for his unusual punctuation. and Capitalization.", "answer": "edward estlin cummings [or e.e. cummings]", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "edward estlin <b><u>cummings</u></b> [or <b><u>e.e. cummings</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["edward estlin cummings", "e.e. cummings"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The Naab is a tributary of this river. This river, which can be crossed via the Szechenyi (\"zay-chen-yee\") Bridge, flows through a city where the Illuminati were founded. The Battle of Nicopolis and Battle of Mohacs occurred along this river. This river splits the old and new parts of a city that contains Heroes Square. A city on this river is home to the (*) Sch\u00f6nbrunn (\"SHAWN-brynn\") Palace and a museum that holds many of Bruegel's (\"brew-gull\") paintings. This river flows through the Iron Gates that separate Romania and Serbia. This river flows through Bratislava, the capital of Slovakia. For 10 points, name this second longest European river that originates in the Black Forest and flows through Budapest and Vienna.", "answer": "Danube River", "subcategory": "Geography", "category": "Geography", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Danube River</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Danube River"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This religion identifies six internal-external pairs of sense-bases that constitute the \"All,\" which is said to be \"burning\" in a sermon by this religion\u2019s founder. Some adherents to this religion progress from Pabbajja (\"puh-bah-jah\") to Upasampada, becoming bhikkhus (\"bee-kh-uhs\"). This religion\u2019s canon is found in a set of scriptures known as the \"three baskets.\" The standard collection of scriptures of one branch of this religion is the (*) Pali Canon. This religion preaches the samsara, a cycle of rebirth that can be ended by attaining nirvana. This religion\u2019s Four Noble Truths describe suffering. For 10 points, name this religion with Theravada and Mahayana branches, based on the teachings of Siddhartha Gautama.", "answer": "Buddhism [accept specific branches like Zen Buddhism, Mahayana Buddhism, or Theravada Buddhism; anti-prompt on specific sects like Yellow Hat or Red Hat]", "subcategory": "Religion", "category": "Religion", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Buddhism</u></b> [accept <b><u>specific branches like Zen Buddhism, Mahayana Buddhism,</u></b> or <b><u>Theravada Buddhism</u></b>; anti-prompt on specific sects like Yellow Hat or Red Hat]", "acceptable": ["Buddhism", "specific branches like Zen Buddhism, Mahayana Buddhism,", "Theravada Buddhism"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This composer of the Dumky Trio wrote an opera in which the title water nymph is helped by the witch Je\u017eibaba (\"yeh-juh-bah-bah\") and sings a \"Song to the Moon.\" This composer of the opera Rusalka also composed a piece with the second movement played (*) \"Largo.\" In that piece, an adagio first movement ends with a theme similar to the spiritual \"Swing Low, Sweet Chariot.\" This composer\u2019s trip to Spillville, Iowa inspired his 12th, or \"American\" string quartet. A theme played by an English horn solo in one of this man\u2019s symphonies inspired the song \"Goin\u2019 Home.\" For 10 points, name this Czech composer of the \"New World Symphony.\"", "answer": "Anton\u00edn Leopold Dvo\u0159\u00e1k", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Anton\u00edn Leopold Dvo\u0159\u00e1k</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Anton\u00edn Leopold Dvo\u0159\u00e1k"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The Birch and Swinnerton-Dyer Conjecture states that if this specific value is plugged into a particular zeta function and the result is zero, then that function will have an infinite number of rational point solutions. According to the Collatz Conjecture, all the hailstone numbers will eventually reach this value. As x approaches zero, (*) sine x over x approaches this value. All parabolas have an eccentricity of this value. This is the number of sides on a M\u00f6bius strip, as well as the value of anything raised to the 0th power. For 10 points, give this only positive integer that is neither prime nor composite.", "answer": "one", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>one</u></b>", "acceptable": ["one"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One general at this battle was told that only wooden walls would keep him and his army safe. A queen in this battle attacked her own allies to confuse the enemy. That action made a king watching this battle say, \"My men have become women, and my women men.\" Queen Artemisia of Halicarnassus crashed her boat into an allied vessel in this battle, where (*) Psyttaleia (\"sit-tuh-lee-ah\") was captured by a general named Aristides. One king in this battle split from Mardonius, who was defeated at Plataea, and this battle occurred right after the battle of Thermopylae. Xerxes I was defeated by the Greeks and their general Themistocles in, for 10 points, what naval battle?", "answer": "Battle of Salamis", "subcategory": "Other History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Battle of Salamis</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Battle of Salamis"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In a novel by this author, the kingdoms of Gup and Chup wage war. \"Dream sequences\" in a novel by this author include one about the death of Allie Cone, and another about Ayesha, who leads a group of pilgrims into the Arabian Sea. This author of Haroun and the Sea of Stories wrote about Mary (*) Pereira's switch of two children at their birth in one novel, while in another, Saladin and Gibreel survive a plane crash over the English Channel. The title characters of a novel by this author include Parvati the Witch and Saleem Sinai, who were born at the exact moment of India\u2019s independence. For 10 points, name this author of The Satanic Verses and Midnight\u2019s Children.", "answer": "Sir Ahmed Salman Rushdie", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Sir Ahmed Salman <b><u>Rushdie</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Sir Ahmed Salman Rushdie"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Matt Bissonnette and Robert O\u2019Neill had differing accounts as to which person carried out this event. Pete Souza took a photograph during this event called Situation Room. When this event was over, the sitting president responded, \"We got him\" after receiving the message \"Geronimo EKIA.\" The target of this event\u2019s body was dumped by the USS Carl Vinson into the North (*) Arabian Sea. This event, codenamed Operation Neptune Spear, occurred after operators including SEAL Team Six were flown into Abbottabad, Pakistan. Barack Obama gave a speech after, for 10 points, what successful assassination of the mastermind behind the 9/11 attacks, the head of Al Qaeda?", "answer": "the killing of Osama bin Mohammed bin Awad bin Laden [accept anything mentioning the death of Osama bin Laden; accept answers replacing \u201cOsama\u201d with \u201cUsama\u201d; accept Operation Neptune Spear before mention]", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>the killing of Osama bin Mohammed bin Awad bin Laden</u></b> [accept <b><u>anything mentioning the death of Osama bin Laden</u></b>; accept <b><u>answers replacing \u201cOsama\u201d with \u201cUsama\u201d</u></b>; accept <b><u>Operation Neptune Spear</u></b> before mention]", "acceptable": ["the killing of Osama bin Mohammed bin Awad bin Laden", "anything mentioning the death of Osama bin Laden", "answers replacing \u201cOsama\u201d with \u201cUsama\u201d", "Operation Neptune Spear"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A figure in a red cloak assists in an action occurring after this scene in a triptych by Peter Paul Rubens. The letters INRI appear above the central figure of this scene in Matthias Grunewald's Isenheim Altarpiece. Three Breton women kneel around the central figure of one depiction of this scene, who is shown with yellow skin, in a Paul Gauguin painting. Two angels wearing green and yellow robes flank the central figure of Raphael's (*) \"Mond\" version of this scene. A burning synagogue with a Lithuanian flag appears at the right of a \"white\" depiction of this scene by Marc Chagall. The Descent From the Cross was painted after, for 10 points, what Biblical scene, which depicts Jesus Christ's death?", "answer": "the Crucifixion of Jesus Christ [accept Mond Crucifixion or White Crucifixion; accept reasonable equivalents, such as Christ on the cross]", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>the Crucifixion of Jesus Christ</u></b> [accept <b><u>Mond Crucifixion</u></b> or <b><u>White Crucifixion</u></b>; accept <b><u>reasonable equivalents, such as Christ on the cross</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["the Crucifixion of Jesus Christ", "Mond Crucifixion", "White Crucifixion", "reasonable equivalents, such as Christ on the cross"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "When parameters are large enough, this scientist theorized that macroscopic and microscopic systems may experience a consistency that they dubbed a \"quantum-classical correspondence.\" A value representing the induced magnetic moment of an electron as a result of its angular momentum is known as this scientist\u2019s namesake (*) \"magneton.\" This scientist postulated that the distance at which electrons orbit a nucleus can be quantified in terms of the reduced Planck\u2019s constant in his namesake model. For 10 points, name this quantum physicist whose atomic model predicted circular orbits and fixed distances between the nucleus and an electron.", "answer": "Niels Henrik David Bohr", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Niels Henrik David Bohr</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Niels Henrik David Bohr"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A former kicker for this team, Cody Parkey, knocked this team out of the 2018 NFL Wild Card Playoffs with his \"double doink\" against the Philadelphia Eagles. This team traded one pick up to get the 2nd overall pick in the 2017 NFL draft and picked the first quarterback of the draft, Mitchell Trubisky. In the 2021 NFL Draft, this team traded up in the first round again to select quarterback Justin (*) Fields. This team also dropped cornerback Kyle Fuller and picked up quarterback Andy Dalton. For 10 points, name this team whose roster includes Allen Robinson II, which rivals the Green Bay Packers and plays home games at Soldier Field in Illinois.", "answer": "Chicago Bears [accept either underlined part]", "subcategory": "Trash", "category": "Trash", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Chicago Bears</u></b> [accept <b><u>either underlined part</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Chicago Bears", "either underlined part"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Karl Rossmann is offered a job at the Hotel Occidental in \"The Stoker,\" which was the first chapter of one of this author\u2019s larger works. Another story by this author centers around a machine composed of the Designer, the Bed, and the Harrow, which inscribes the words \"Be Just!\" on the Officer. This author of Amerika and \"In the (*) Penal Colony\" wrote about a character who dies \"like a dog\" after being arrested for an unspecified crime. The protagonist of his most famous work wishes to send his sister, Grete, to study violin at the Conservatory. For 10 points, name this Czech author who wrote about Josef K. in The Trial and Gregor Samsa\u2019s transformation into a bug in \"The Metamorphosis.\"", "answer": "Franz Kafka", "subcategory": "Other Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Franz <b><u>Kafka</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Franz Kafka"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In Orphic traditions, this deity was born to Persephone, but was ripped apart and eaten by Titans shortly thereafter. This reincarnation of Zagreus is the subject of an epic by Nonnus, in which they attack India after their lover, Ampelos, dies and becomes a vine. After offending this deity, Lycurgus was inflicted with madness. This god\u2019s crazed followers, the (*) maenads, killed Orpheus. In one story, this god turned a group of pirates who attempted to kidnap him into dolphins. This god was sewn into Zeus\u2019s thigh after his mother Semele disintegrated while looking at Zeus in his full form. For 10 points, name this \"twice-born\" god of wine.", "answer": "Dionysus [accept Zagreus before mention; do NOT accept or prompt on \"Bacchus\"]", "subcategory": "Mythology", "category": "Mythology", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Dionysus</u></b> [accept <b><u>Zagreus</u></b> before mention; do NOT accept or prompt on \"Bacchus\"]", "acceptable": ["Dionysus", "Zagreus"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This organization conducted central meetings called Tagfahrt, and it had earlier formed the Confederation of Cologne after the Battle of Helsingborg (\"HELL-sing-bog\"). This organization was given 15% of the profit of one country\u2019s trade by King Valdemar IV (\"the fourth\"). London\u2019s Cannon Street Station was used as a steelyard by this organization, which was opposed by one that later called themselves the \"Equal Sharers,\" the Victual Brothers. This organization constructed the warship Adler von (*) Lubeck, named after its base. Visby and Bryggen were Kontors, or trading posts, used by, for 10 points, what organization that held a monopoly in the Baltic and Northern Seas and rivaled the Kalmar Union?", "answer": "Hanseatic League [accept Hansa]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Hanseatic League</u></b> [accept <b><u>Hansa</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Hanseatic League", "Hansa"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This state\u2019s Moosehead Lake is the source of the Kennebec River, which runs through this state\u2019s capital. This state\u2019s Baxter State Park contains its tallest point, Mount Katahdin. Eagle Lake and Cadillac Mountain are located in a national park in this state. One country\u2019s Campobello Island is only connected to land by a bridge in this state. Presque Isle is in this state\u2019s (*) Aroostook (\"UH-roo-stook\") County, which fought a \"bloodless war\" with Canada. This state only borders one other state, New Hampshire. Mount Desert Island is the site of Acadia National Park in, for 10 points, what state with cities such as Portland and Bangor, and capital at Augusta?", "answer": "Maine", "subcategory": "Geography", "category": "Geography", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Maine</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Maine"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Bogorad\u2019s syndrome causes this substance to be produced when eating. The lipid component of this substance, produced by meibomian glands in the tarsal plates, is combined with an aqueous component rich in lipocalin, lactoferrin, and lysozyme. Secretion of this substance is associated with globus pharyngis, a sensation caused by inflammation in the throat. This substance, which is overproduced in dacryorrhea (\"dack-ree-oh-ree-ah\"), is secreted by the (*) lacrimal glands. The basal type of this substance functions as a lubricant, the reflex type is used to wash out irritants, and the emotional type is produced in response to stress. For 10 points, name this substance released near the eyes.", "answer": "tears", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>tears</u></b>", "acceptable": ["tears"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A Wall Street Journal opinion article caused controversy when it argued that a member of this family should drop their \"Dr.\" title. This family owns the German shepherd Champ. During a Las Vegas election briefing, a man wearing a \"BBQ, Beer, Freedom\" shirt claimed that this family was \"stealing the election.\" A member of this family's laptop was found at a (*) Wilmington, Delaware computer repair shop. In a \"perfect phone call\" that led to his first impeachment, Donald Trump asked Volodymyr (\"voh-low-dee-meer\") Zelensky to investigate a member of this family. For 10 points, name this family that includes Jill, Hunter, and the current president, Joe.", "answer": "Biden family [accept the \"Biden crime family\"; accept Dr. Jill Tracy Jacobs Biden, Robert Hunter Biden, or Joseph Robinette \"Joe\" Biden Jr.]", "subcategory": "Current Events", "category": "Current Events", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Biden family</u></b> [accept the <b><u>\"Biden crime family</u></b>; accept <b><u>Dr. Jill Tracy Jacobs Biden, Robert Hunter Biden,</u></b> or <b><u>Joseph Robinette \"Joe\" Biden Jr.</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Biden family", "\"Biden crime family", "Dr. Jill Tracy Jacobs Biden, Robert Hunter Biden,", "Joseph Robinette \"Joe\" Biden Jr."], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "While being arrested, the protagonist of this novel hears a voice say \"here comes a chopper to chop off your head,\" completing a rhyme about oranges and lemons. The protagonist of this novel reads a book comparing Death Worship and Neo-Bolshevism written about \"Oligarchical Collectivism.\" This book opens on a \"bright cold day in April\" when \"the clocks were striking (*) thirteen.\" In this novel, the linguist Syme defines words such as \"doubleplusgood\" before becoming an unperson. At the end of this novel, the protagonist accepts that 2 + 2 = 5 and exclaims \"do it to Julia!\" while being tortured by O\u2019Brien with rats in Room 101. For 10 points, name this dystopian novel about Winston Smith by George Orwell.", "answer": "1984", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>1984</u></b>", "acceptable": ["1984"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}], "bonuses": []}